Guide to the Judy Alter Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
Judy Alter Accessions
circa 1972-2019
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Alter, Judy, 1938-
UPWC.93057
22 boxes Plus oversize
Judy Alter began donating her papers to the Southwestern Writers Collection/The Wittliff Collections in 1993. Alter writes for both adults and young readers and she is best known for her books on women and girls of the American West. Among her many honors are "best book" awards from the Texas Institute of Letters, the Western Writers of America, and the Western Heritage (Wrangler) Awards from the National Cowboy Museum. In 1996 the Dallas Morning News named her one of 100 Women Who Have Left Their Mark on Texas. In 2005 the Western Writers of America gave Alter the Owen Wister Award for Lifetime Achievement.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Judy Alter, 2019.
Scope and Contents
Judy Alter Accessions, The Wittliff Collections, Texas State University.
Index Terms
Subjects
Women authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Young Adult Fiction; Western stories; Detective and mystery stories; Cookbooks
Subjects (Persons)
Alter, Judy, 1938-
- 1993-057
  Abstract
  Research, manuscripts, correspondence and galley proofs for several works by Judy Alter, along with manuscripts for Alter's early unpublished novels. Also included are editorial files for Larry L. King's Golden Shadows Old West Museum, which was published in 1993 by Texas Christian University Press, where Judy Alter serves as Director.
  - "Luke and the Van Zandt County War" manuscripts and galleys, undated (Box 13-16)
  - "Mattie" research, correspondence, manuscripts, and galleys, undated (Box 13-16)
  - Unfinished novel loosely based on the life of artist "Rufus F. Zogbaum", undated (Box 13-16)
  - Draft for "Elmer Kelton and West Texas: A Literary Relationship", undated (Box 13-16)
  - "A Man in the Window"—unpublished novel, undated (Box 13-16)
  - Book reviews from the "El Paso Times and Dallas Morning News", undated (Box 13-16)
  - Manuscripts for "Growing Up in the Old West" and "Great Women in the Old West", undated (Box 13-16)
  - "Katie and the Recluse" manuscript, undated (Box 13-16)
  - "Libbie" research; manuscript for this novel based on the life of "Elizabeth Bacon Custer", undated (Box 13-16)
  - "A Ballad for Sallie" manuscripts and galley proofs, undated (Box 13-16)
  - Material for "Jeanne Williams Western Writers Series" pamphlet, undated (Box 13-16)
  - Clippings on Judy Alter, undated (Box 13-16)
  - "So Far from Paradise" manuscript and clippings for this novel commissioned by the "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" in conjunction with the "Texas Sesquicentennial", 1986 (Box 13-16)
  - Unfinished YA [young adult] novel notated: "My first attempt at fiction- probably 1975-76", 1975-1976 (Box 13-16)
  - Unfinished YA novel 2, undated (Box 13-16)
  - "Dorothy Johnson" material for "Western Writers Series" pamphlet, undated (Box 13-16)
  - 10 folders on the "Golden Shadows Old West Museum: manuscripts and galley proofs", undated (Box 13-16)
  - "Texas Folklore Society" program, 1993 (Box 13-16)
  - "Unfinished 2nd novel", undated (Box 13-16)
  - Original illustrations for "Luke and the Van Zandt County War", undated (Box 13-16)
  - Publisher's paste-ups for "Eli Whitney", undated (Box 13-16)
- 1993-199
  Materials pertaining to the writing career of Judy Alter.
  - Typed manuscript and galleys for "After Pa Was Shot", published by "William Morrow and Co.", 1978 (Box 0014)
- 1994-045
  - Typed manuscript (with emendations and printer's notes); cover for "Libbie" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 0014)
- 1996-067
  - Two typescript drafts (and correspondence from publisher) for "Cherokee Rose" or "Ride a Wild Horse" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 0061)
  - Typescript for "Jessie" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 0061)
- 1997-050
  - Notes; galley proofs; typescript; proofreader copy; and letter regarding Alter's book "Rodeos: The Greatest Show on Dirt", undated (Box 0050)
- 2004-170
  Materials pertaining to the writing career of Judy Alter
  - Typed manuscript titled "Laura Ingalls Wilder: A Biography" by Judy Alter with note: "Never published - the editor at 'Grober' accused me of 'plagiarism' and I never got another assignment from them. It was a trumped-up charge leveled at several other writers at the same time, my lawyer wrote - it turned into quite a'brouhaha'.", undated (Box 493, Folder 1)
  - Incomplete "untitled" typed manuscript, a sequel to "So Far from Paradise", undated (Box 493, Folder 2)
  - Annotated typed manuscript titled, "The (Faithful) Fearful Heart" by Judy Alter with note: "My one disastrous attempt at romance, trite!", undated (Box 493, Folder 3)
  - Typed manuscript titled, "Potter's Wife: A novel of Chicago" by Judy Alter; rejection letters, undated (Box 493, Folder 4)
  - Typed manuscript titled, "Potter's Wife" by Judy Alter with note: "An early version of a novel I still hope will come to something", undated (Box 493, Folder 5)
  - Annotated manuscript titled, "Haley Goes to Camp" by Judy Alter with note: "This shows how far this had gone before publication was cancelled", undated (Box 493, Folder 6)
  - Annotated "untitled" typed manuscript by Judy Alter with note: "Publisher went out of business, book was never published. I had to get my lawyer to collect the 'Work-for-hire' fee", undated (Box 493, Folder 7)
  - Annotated page proofs for "Cissie Palmer: Putting Wealth to Work" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 493, Folder 8)
  - Typed short story titled, "Prisoners", which was published in "Collective Heart", undated (Box 493, Folder 9)
  - Typed manuscript titled, "The Perfect Coed" by Judy Alter with note: "My first and so far, only attempt at my story- still want to do it", various reject letters from publishers, undated (Box 493, Folder 10)
  - Annotated typed manuscript titled, "I Wish I Lived in Eleanor Lee's House" a novel by Judy Alter, undated (Box 493, Folder 11)
  - Typed manuscript that was never published titled, "I Wish I Lived in Eleanor Lee's House" a novel by Judy Alter, undated (Box 493, Folder 12)
  - Typed manuscript titled, "So Far from Paradise" a novel by Judy Alter with note: "This novel was commissioned by the 'Fort Worth Star Telegram' and ran serially as a part of their sesquicentennial features. Later submitted on request, to this development company which was booking for 'Disney' projects, I think", undated (Box 493, Folder 13)
  - List of books; short stories; reviews; columns; and articles written by Judy Alter, undated (Box 493, Folder 14)
- 2007-073
  Material consists mainly of "working files for children's books now in print". Research material consists of newspaper clippings, information from the internet, and photocopies from various books and other sources. In a few instances, original file folders were kept because of notes or other writings that appear on them. Folder 20 has been flagged for sensitive material.
  - "Kemah"– notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings, undated (Box 811, Folder 1)
  - "Australia"– notes, correspondence, research material, newspaper clippings and drafts, undated (Box 811, Folder 2)
  - "Becoming American"– notes and research material, undated (Box 811, Folder 3)
  - "Devil Amongst Us"– correspondence with "Eakin Press"; publishing contract; newspaper clippings; notes; royalty statements; and two copies of "The Children's Book catalog" from "Eakin Press", Fall 1996 (Box 811, Folder 4)
  - "Etta Place"– statements from "Dorchester Publishing" for "Sundance, Butch and Me", undated (Box 811, Folder 5)
  - "Lamar"– notes, research material, and newspaper clippings of book reviews, undated (Box 811, Folder 6)
  - "Compass Point"– correspondence, notes, and research material, undated (Box 811, Folder 7)
  - "Cissy-used files"– notes and correspondence, undated (Box 811, Folder 8)
  - "Missouri"– notes, draft, and research material, undated (Box 811, Folder 9)
  - "Crystal City/Buddy Guyler"– correspondence and newspaper clipping, undated (Box 811, Folder 10)
  - "Child's World"– correspondence, undated (Box 811, Folder 11)
  - "Ellen Temple"– correspondence from publisher, undated (Box 811, Folder 12)
  - "Susan Wallace"– 1953 letter to Lewis Wallace from Blair Taylor, undated (Box 811, Folder 13)
  - "Edom"– notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings, undated (Box 811, Folder 14)
  - "Gail Sheehy Focus Group"– correspondence, undated (Box 811, Folder 15)
  - "Spokane"– correspondence, travel material such as hotel receipts, rental car and plane information, two color photos and newspaper clippings, undated (Box 811, Folder 16)
  - "No. America"– notes and drafts, newspaper clippings, research material, and correspondence, undated (Box 811, Folder 17)
  - "Illinois"– notes, correspondence, research material and draft with notes, undated (Box 811, Folder 18)
  - "Wilder 2"– correspondence, research material, newspaper clippings, and draft with notes all relating to work on "Laura Ingalls Wilder", undated (Box 811, Folder 19)
  - "Enslow Pubs"– material from publisher includes correspondence, writing agreements and research material, undated (Box 811, Folder 20)
  - "Ballad for Sallie"– invitations for book release, writing agreements, newspaper clippings, correspondence, reviews and three book covers for "Ballad for Sallie", undated (Box 811, Folder 21)
- 2008-085
  Material consists mainly of drafts from both "soon to be published" and unpublished material.
  - "Passenger Ship"– includes handwritten notes and some pages from manuscript with editorial comments, undated (Box 1053, Folder 1)
  - "Texas Women"– research material including newspaper clippings and printouts from various internet sources, undated (Box 1053, Folder 2)
  - "Vaccines"– handwritten notes; research material from internet sources; and a writer's agreement for the work, undated (Box 1053, Folder 3)
  - "Women's Rights"– handwritten notes; editorial comments; emails; and a writer's agreement for the work, undated (Box 1053, Folder 4)
  - "Dead Space"- draft "Dead Space" by Judy Alter with revisions, July 7, 2007 (Box 1053, Folder 5)
  - Page proofs of "Women's Rights" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 1053, Folder 6)
  - Draft of "Audie Murphy, War Hero and Movie Star" with notes, undated (Box 1053, Folder 7)
  - Page proofs for "Surgery, Passenger Ships, and Vaccines" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 1053, Folder 8)
  - "Dead Space" by Judy Alter, marked: "first draft February 2007" with handwritten notes, undated (Box 1053, Folder 9)
  - "Sue Ellen Learns to Dance and Other Stories" by Judy Alter with notes, undated (Box 1053, Folder 10)
  - "Life with Food, Books, and Kids" by Judy Alter with notes, undated (Box 1053, Folder 11)
  - "Manuscript of Potter's Wife" by Judy Alter, undated (Box 1053, Folder 12-13)
  - "Dead Space" by Judy Alter, second draft, February 2007 (Box 1053, Folder 14)
- 2009-030
  Material contains drafts, research, and numerous newspaper clippings related to Alter's writing; original file labels appear in quotation marks.
  - Label from folder was missing– contains drafts of speeches, or talks; numerous topics include women, writing, and women and the West, undated (Box 1097, Folder 1-2)
  - "Upcoming Engagements", undated (Box 1097, Folder 3)
  - "Texas Writers Column"– notes, drafts, and numerous newspaper clippings of Alter's column, undated (Box 1097, Folder 4-5)
  - "Owen Wister Award", undated (Box 1097, Folder 6)
  - "Judy Personal", undated (Box 1097, Folder 7-8)
  - "Judy Personal Two", undated (Box 1097, Folder 9-10)
  - "Judy Personal Three", undated (Box 1097, Folder 11-12)
- 2010-066
  Material donated from Alter's files; items include magazines, writer contracts, reviews, newspaper clippings, limited correspondence, and some research material. All original folder titles appear in quotation marks.
  - "Cowboys & Country" magazine; "Old West Summer '95"; "Hood 7 Somervell Today" magazine, Spring/Summer 1987;Fall '95/Winter '96; 1995; March 2009 (Box 1259, Folder 1)
  - "True West" magazine, January 1994; March 1995; January 1996; February 1996; May 1996; May 1997 (Box 1259, Folder 2)
  - "Persimmon Hill" magazine;"Texas Journal" magazine, Spring 1991; Autumn 1992; Autumn 1993; Spring/Summer 1991; Spring/Summer 1999 (Box 1259, Folder 3)
  - "Texas Co-Op Power" magazine [more than one copy of some issues], February 1996; May 2006; September 2006; November 2006; April 2007; January 2008; June 2008 (Box 1259, Folder 4)
  - "Roundup Magazine" [two copies]; "Louis L'Amour" [three copies], June 1999; August 2000; June 2005; July 1995 (Box 1259, Folder 5)
  - "Fort Worth, Texas"; "Aura of Fort Worth", December 1998; February 1999; April 1999; November/December 1993; January/February 1994; November/December 1994 (Box 1259, Folder 6)
  - "Aura of Dallas Fort Worth"; "Fort Worth, Texas", March/April 1994; May/June 1994; July/August 1994; September/October 1994; March/April 1995; February 1999; May 1999 (Box 1259, Folder 7)
  - "Book Reviews", undated (Box 1259, Folder 8)
  - "John Barclay Armstrong", undated (Box 1259, Folder 9)
  - "Audie Murphy", undated (Box 1259, Folder 10)
  - "Cherokee"- relating to book "Cherokee Rose", undated (Box 1259, Folder 11)
  - "Custer Reviews"- relating to book "Libbie", undated (Box 1259, Folder 12)
  - "After Pa Was Shot- reprint", undated (Box 1259, Folder 13)
  - "Great African Americans", undated (Box 1259, Folder 14)
  - "Henrietta King", undated (Box 1259, Folder 15)
  - "Martin de Leon", undated (Box 1259, Folder 16)
  - "Extraordinary Women (of the American West)", undated (Box 1259, Folder 17)
  - "Publicity - Judy", undated (Box 1259, Folder 18)
  - Material removed from "untitled" folder relating to "Pocahontas" manuscript, includes related correspondence, undated (Box 1260, Folder 1)
  - "Oprah Winfrey", undated (Box 1260, Folder 2)
  - "Runaway Serape", undated (Box 1260, Folder 3)
  - "Sam H", undated (Box 1260, Folder 4)
  - "From Paradise", undated (Box 1260, Folder 5)
  - "Mattie", undated (Box 1260, Folder 6)
  - "Miscellaneous publicity", undated (Box 1260, Folder 7)
  - "Mattie -reprint", undated (Box 1260, Folder 8)
  - "Ma Ferguson", undated (Box 1260, Folder 9)
  - "Surgery", undated (Box 1260, Folder 10)
  - "Cookbook", undated (Box 1260, Folder 11)
  - "Women of the West, 2000" (Box 1260, Folder 12)
  - "Short Stories", undated (Box 1260, Folder 13)
  - Assorted newspapers and newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1260, Folder 14)
- 2011-155
  Donation includes research files, manuscripts, and drafts of the author's work.
  - "Research for Extraordinary Women of the American West"– includes printouts from the internet and handwritten notes, undated (Box 1377, Folder 1-4)
  - "Draft of 1st 8 chapters" of "No Neighborhood for Old Women", August 8, 2008 (Box 1377, Folder 5)
  - "Partial rough draft" of "No Neighborhood for Old Women", undated (Box 1377, Folder 6)
  - "2nd pass " of "Cooking My Way through Life with Kids and Books", February 2, 2009 (Box 1377, Folder 7)
  - Draft, with revisions, of "Cooking My Way through Life with Kids and Books"; includes one piece of correspondence, undated (Box 1377, Folder 8)
  - Draft of "Skeleton in a Dead Space: A Kelly Jones Mystery", undated (Box 1377, Folder 9)
  - Draft of "Texas is Chili Country", undated (Box 1377, Folder 10)
  - Draft of "No Neighborhood for Old Women" with notations, undated (Box 1377, Folder 11)
  - Draft of "Skeleton in a Dead Space" "edited", November 8, 2009 (Box 1377, Folder 12)
  - "For Archive"– newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1377, Folder 13)
  - "Overdue"– correspondence; short story "The Library Cat's Magical Christmas", undated (Box 1377, Folder 14)
  - "Dead Space"– correspondence; publishers lists; limited printouts, undated (Box 1377, Folder 15)
  - Two copies of magazine "Living with Panache" article on Judy Alter, page 16, undated (Box 1377, Folder 16)
  - Draft of "A Blue Plate Café Mystery", undated (Box 1377, Folder 17)
  - Draft of "Skeleton in a Dead Space: A Kelly Jones Mystery", "later revised", Fall 2010 (Box 1377, Folder 18)
- 2013-091
  This donation consists of manuscript drafts and speeches written by author Judy Alter. Included in this collection are early drafts for Trouble in a Big Box, Danger Comes Home, No Neighborhood for Old Women, Cooking My Way Through Life with Kids & Books, and Texas is Chili Country. Also included is unpublished material related to "Gail Borden" and a Certificate of Copyright Registration for Great Texas Chefs.
  - Letter from Judy Alter to Steve Davis, undated (Box 1736, Folder 1)
  - Speech for "A Celebration of Texas Writers: Exploring Women of the American West with Judy Alter" at Baylor University, April 16, 2012 (Box 1736, Folder 2)
  - Speech for the opening of the "UCC Women's Luncheon", September 9, 2012 (Box 1736, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of Copyright Registration for "Great Texas Chefs", undated (Box 1736, Folder 4)
  - "Trouble in a Big Box"-draft, October 5 (Box 1736, Folder 5)
  - "Trouble in a Big Box"-early draft, plus a letter with comments from "Genie", December 14, 2011 (Box 1736, Folder 6)
  - "Trouble in a Big Box"-draft, December 1 (Box 1736, Folder 7)
  - "Trouble in a Big Box"-draft plus editor's notes, undated (Box 1736, Folder 8)
  - "Danger Comes Home"-draft, March 27 (Box 1736, Folder 9)
  - "Danger Comes Home"-draft with some revisions, undated (Box 1736, Folder 10)
  - "Danger Comes Home"-draft, plus mentor's comments, December 5, 2012 (Box 1736, Folder 11)
  - "No Neighborhood for Old Women"-draft, July 5, 2008 (Box 1736, Folder 12)
  - "Cooking My Way Through Life with Kids & Books"-draft, undated (Box 1736, Folder 13)
  - "A Frontier Childhood/Gail Borden" -draft, never published, undated (Box 1736, Folder 14)
  - "A Frontier Childhood/Gail Borden"-draft, "another version," never published, undated (Box 1736, Folder 15)
  - "­­Texas is Chili Country"-first draft, revised, September 2012 (Box 1736, Folder 16)
- 2014-133
  Additional material for the Judy Alter archive. This donation contains correspondence 2011-2012, drafts, publicity, and reviews related to Alter's Kelly O'Connell mystery series.
  - "Kelly Two Marketing," Publicity; Correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 1870, Folder 1)
  - "Kelly # 3," Publicity; Reviews; Correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 1870, Folder 2)
  - "Untitled" draft with corrections by Mary Dulle, September 27, 2013 (Box 1870, Folder 3)
  - "Deception in Strange Places: A Kelly O'Connell Mystery", printout draft with some corrections, 2013 (Box 1870, Folder 4)
  - "Kelly O'Connell #6", Printout draft; Fred Erismais' copy with corrections, June 24, 2014 (Box 1870, Folder 5)
  - "Kelly O'Connell #6", Printout draft; Fred Erismais' copy lacks final edits, August 7, 2014 (Box 1870, Folder 6)
- 2015-038
  This addition to Alter's collection includes a draft of The Perfect Coed, and various magazines in which her articles have been featured such as Louis L'amour Western Magazine, Texas Co-Op Power, and Roundup Magazine.
  - Issues of "Texas Co-Op Power", featuring Alter's "Footnotes" column, undated (Box 1883, Folder 12)
  - Various magazines featuring interviews with Alter: "Louis L'amour Western Magazine"; "Roundup Magazine"; "Living with Panache", undated (Box 1883, Folder 13)
  - Draft of "The Perfect Coed", April 2013 (Box 1883, Folder 14)
- 2019-107
  This collection consists of additional material of Judy Alter's literary papers. The majority of the material within the collection is a series of books written by Judy Alter. Also included in the collection is many magazines, the majority being from or dealing with Fort Worth, Texas. Many newspapers are included in the collection, each containing an article about or written by Judy Alter. The folder titles preceding a semicolon reflect Alter's original description.
  - "The Dallas Morning News"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clippings, September 3,1972-February 18,1973 (Box 3128, Folder 1)
  - Papers by Judy Alter discussing Jane Austen and Lola Montez; and the "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clipping, October 22, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 2)
  - Paper discussing a book and describing "Willy Women of the West"; letter from "Naylor Company"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clipping, June 11, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 3)
  - Paper on "The Nixon's"; paper on "Sean"; and "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clippings, April 9, 1972-June 25, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 4)
  - Paper on "Your Money or Your Life"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clipping; letter for "Duet in Diamonds", April 9, 1972-July 9, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 5)
  - Paper on "Anthony Trollope and Private Faces/Public Places"; "Fort Worth Star- Telegram" clippings, August 13, 1972- August 20, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 6)
  - "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clippings; paper on "The Golden Book of Jewish Humor", October 1, 1971 -April 2, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 7)
  - "Fort Worth Star-Telegram"; paper on "Pearl S. Buck", February 5, 1972- February 13, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 8)
  - Paper on "Change in the Wind": "Fort Worth Star-Telegram", February 27, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 9)
  - Paper on "This Man David"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clipping, March 19, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 10)
  - Paper on "Growing Up Female in America and Out of my Time"; "Fort Worth Star- Telegram" clipping, January 2, 1972- January 23, 1972 (Box 3128, Folder 11)
  - "Star-Telegram"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clippings, 1974-1980 (Box 3128, Folder 12)
  - "Doctors and Dalliance" paper; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram", 1974-1975 (Box 3128, Folder 13)
  - "Right Now"; "Fort Worth Star-Telegram" clippings, 1975-1979 (Box 3128, Folder 14)
  - "The Fort Worth Story", copy of chapters, 1967 (Box 3128, Folder 15)
  - "Readers' Copy: Murder at Peacock Mansion", July 2015 (Box 3128, Folder 16)
  - "Judy Alter" newspaper clippings; "Scene" magazine; invitation; and card, 1978-1997 (Box 3128, Folder 17)
  - "McCloud: An Eastern Western", March 21, 1975 (Box 3128, Folder 18)
  - "Sundance Books for Young Readers" pamphlet; "A Mystery Beyond the Ordinary" by Judy Alter, 1984-1985 (Box 3128, Folder 19)
  - "Voter's Guide to Democratic Candidates", undated (Box 3128, Folder 20)
  - "Radio Tape: People's Health"; ¼ inch open reel tape, Spring 1965 (Box 3128, Reel 21)
  - "Scene Magazine"; "The Dallas Morning News", 1980-1982 (Box 3129, Folder 1)
  - "Scene Magazine" multiple issues, 1980-1982 (Box 3129, Folder 2)